my name is David fuller and a journalist
and I've recently started teaching men's
work and this is a bit of a story about
how I got into men's work what I got out
of it and it's about masculinity it's
about my relationship with my father
it's a very personal story but I hope
that it's also in some way Universal
I've told it to people in the past it's
sort of yeah it seems to connect with
something quite deep in the experience
of having a father and maybe not getting
on so well with your father and then
trying to rebuild that light that that
relationship in in the later years of
your life so we're going to pull back
and start this story back in 2011 in
Libya I used to be a foreign producer
with channel 4 news Tripoli was falling
Gaddafi was on the run
we came into Tripoli just as Gaddafi's
regime was crumbling
this is centre of Tripoli just as
everything's going completely mental so
yeah then so shortly after that we got
to get out Gaddafi's tent this is the
burnt out Gaddafi's tent in the center
of Tripoli and around us all of these
guns are going off people firing into
the air it's just this incredible moment
there's a few times in my journalistic
career or I felt I'm in the middle of
history this is just an extraordinary
place an extraordinary experience and we
had a satellite phone I thought I really
want to share this so I called my
parents called my mom and she answered
the phone and I said listen listen to
this just crazy crazy moment guns going
off everywhere and she started crying
and I said okay I'm not in danger and
she then said I'm at the hospital with
your dad he's just been diagnosed with
stomach cancer and we don't know much
but we know that stomach cancer is is a
diagnosis of stomach cancer usually
means it's pretty advanced and we think
it's pretty bad and he he was young he
was fit he'd just been on cycling
holiday the literally just the week
before and so it's completely unexpected
completely out of the blue and I knew it
wasn't good I started crying as well on
the phone and my bosses at Channel 4
News thankfully just put me on a plane
straight back to to the UK and so as
we're in the plane going back to the UK
I'm just going to take a little
digression and fill in the gaps because
growing up I didn't get on well with my
father at all we always fought and we
still didn't get on even in 2011 just
before this happened and I to be honest
I was I was a bit of a little shit to
him growing up I used to kind of take
the piss out of him I used to there was
a sort of conspiracy with my mother
against him
and I was I I never worked this out
worked out why for a long time but I was
really nasty to him I push him I'm
pushing my pushing and I I remember one
time I pushed him so much that he
grabbed me by my throat and held me up
against the wall and it didn't it didn't
sort of dawn on me until later and there
was kind of a real sense of euphoria
when I got when that happened as well it
never dawned on me until later why that
had happened it took me quite a long
time to work it out and a lot of it was
through the kind of the men's work and
the inner work that I'd done after that
that I sort of started to make sense of
it so my parents were very left-wing
very idealistic my childhood was like
CMD marchers delivering leaflets for the
Labour Party they were very rebellious
as well and naturism now for about the
next couple of minutes I'm gonna be
speaking with a picture of my naked
father behind me but it's what he would
have wanted so my father was very much a
kind of new man he wanted to be very
different from the male role models that
he had and he wanted to kind of yeah be
non-competitive and be be someone
different from from his father and what
he'd seen growing up very
non-competitive mber when we were played
when we played football me and my
brother he'd say why do you have to have
a goal I couldn't just pass it to each
other
and it took me a while but underneath he
was he was really opinionated he was
really stubborn he always thought he was
right very different from me everybody
knows he lies and he could also get
really really angry and want his own way
and I think that's what I was doing when
I pushed him just sort of pushing that
point like to say I know that that's not
that that's not authentic that kind of
non competitive age there's something
more there and I pushed him until he
until he snapped until I found it and my
mum told me later on that just that
moment really traumatized him like him
really it took him a long time to get
over that that that I pushed him to that
point that he grabbed me and that he
realized that he had that in him and it
took it took a lot a lot of sort of
transformational work after that where I
started to really unpack the the anger
that I had towards my father and to
really kind of understand it and and
recognize that all the things that I
disliked in him I I had it I had all of
those things in myself and was really
able to kind of understand the shadow of
what what I was pushing out in him was
something that I also had because my my
experience of men's work is that I can
speak to myself as a man I have those
those edges I have that aggression I
have that wanting to be right I have
that wanting to dominate I have all of
these things that can come out and my
experience is it's only through fully
recognizing those and integrating them
that I've become more hold as a man to
to do what you could call the shadow
work of really kind of looking at myself
really deeply and then taking that anger
taking that aggression and using it
integrating it into the personality and
then becoming sort of more more present
more powerful it becomes I think once
integrated a form of sort of personal
power and becomes a kind of fuel for
certainly it's become a kind of fuel for
my life and over probably since about
2006 when I first started doing
workshops and starting doing this work
this sort of in a work from a place of
crisis in myself that I started to
really kind of integrate some of these
things and on some level I started to
heal at least some of the relationship
with him in my
self although at this point we haven't
kind of healed it in the in the outside
world so planes now about to land in in
the UK and I go straight down to
Southampton to see my dad in the
hospital and he's outside in the garden
with my mom and a family friend and I
just go up to him and I embrace him and
for my friend after a few minutes my
friend takes this picture which is one
of the most precious things I have in my
life I think how probably lasted for
about 10 minutes it might have been even
more sort of time stopped and my friend
realized at some point that he was in
the presence of something special and
got his phone out and took this picture
and something something I think very
profound happened in that moment some
kind of healing happened and I've had a
few friends who've looked at this friend
of mine touched it up and has turned it
into a picture I have my wall at home
and there's something about the way he's
kind of collapsing into me and I'm
holding him that's a kind of a transfer
of some kind of I don't know as a child
taking something and taking it from my
father that that from what then happened
I feel that that's what happened in that
moment and I think what happened here
catalyzed a lot of what happened next
because shortly after that he got the
diagnosis and he was diagnosed with
three months to live and that makes
makes things real obviously and I I then
wrote him a letter and I said I said
look I've been doing all of this work
I've done all these workshops and I get
these reflections from people in these
workshops where people say they talk
about my authenticity or they talk about
my honesty or and I realize these are
your qualities I realized that I got
them from you and I've never been able
to admit that to you I've never been
able to to recognize all the good that I
got from you
and he was very touched by that letter
and then I thought well this is he's
gonna be dead in three months why
doesn't everyone I don't want to hear
his funeral stuff that people should
have said to him before so I'll ain't
got in touch with all of his friends all
of the family everyone that used to work
with as many people as I could and said
he's gonna be dead in three months I
want to hit I want you to what you might
want to say at the funeral wanted to say
it now and send it to him and so over
the next three months as he was becoming
more and more ill lying in bed my mum
was reading these to him and all of this
amazing stuff started coming in from
former friends work colleagues family so
he was an arts officer for the council
and created the Southampton Film Fest of
all save the Theatre Royal in Winchester
created the street parties in the road
and my father's like core wound was that
he really didn't think he'd achieve very
much in his life he he had a real down
on himself and felt that he'd been a
failure he'd never read amounted to much
and this this had really eaten away at
him and then somehow in the last three
months of his life some of that change
some of that shifted just from the
weight of all this stuff coming in and
the sheer love an outpouring of stuff
that came in and I'm sure that part of
that was catalyzed by that one moment
and that one healing that I was able to
do and then to be there for him and then
to produce I turned him yeah I'm sure
it's catalyzed by this by this moment
and then I I made a I took all of those
and made it into a book that I gave to
him for his for his birthday sort of
about three weeks before he died because
there was also when when things like
this happen there's there's a Jordan
Peterson quote where he talks about be
the person to rely on in a funeral it's
hard enough in a funeral but it can be
absolute hell
if you haven't dealt with your family
stuff and I really feel because all
sorts of stuff came in some people are
in denial some people are in don't want
to know I mean other members of my
family just wanted it to go away they
weren't ready for I feel that I I was
able to be there because of the work
that I'd done and yeah it turned into a
really beautiful experience rather than
being absolute hell even though we were
all there when he died we we were
holding hands around his bed when he
died and it was it was very yeah it was
it was one of the most I now look back
on it it's one of the most precious
moments of my life and it's a it's a
wonderful it's a it's a wonderful story
and it's often I told this sort of over
the last few years and this is normally
where it ends and it's but it's not
where it ends because as someone who had
I believed my father's image of himself
like I I treated a Miss this failure
growing up I'd realized that I didn't
turn alized the story that he hadn't
treated him the same way to kind of
treated himself and then to have all of
this come on at the age of 36 to realize
by the time he was my age he'd opened an
Arts Centre he saved a theater he'd
created the South Hampton Film Festival
he'd had three kids it's like oh this
guy I thought was a failure at a chief
farm or that that stays that I had and
there's also something that in my
experience when your father goes as a
man that's there's something archetypal
even though I didn't get on that well my
father there's something there that's
missing this sort of archetypal
grounding point and I really found that
I had to go on a journey of myself over
the next sort of six months to really
find my path and find what I needed to
do and it was it then became like the
hardest period of my life like I've had
some real ups and downs over the last
six years just really trying to get my
shit together and decide what it was
that was meant to be doing with my life
and what I was meant to be bringing into
the world yeah it was pretty hard and
yeah it's only in the last year I feel
that I've really started to come out of
that and realize what it is that I'm
supposed to be doing
and it's sort of its leading men's work
use my journalistic skills to tell the
stories of this kind of transformational
work and then to lead the work because
you can only you can't you can't show
someone a film and give them a
transformational experience you've got
to give the transformational experience
as well and this is the work that I'm
most passionate about and this is what I
found the most helpful in my in my
personal journey and we consciously in
our workshops we consciously bring in
support of the father it's a very kind
of emotional piece for a lot of men to
to feel that to model some some healthy
father energy in that workshop space and
we had a guy a father and our last
workshop who said he he really wanted to
go away and give that to his son so I
you know as always writing this
yesterday kind of I wish that my father
had had some of this and maybe the
relationship that I have with him would
have been a bit different but he did the
best he could and I'm really grateful
for that and I just want to yeah honor
him by raising a toast to Michael -
Michael
[Applause]